Finding Aid for Emerson F. Powrie and Gwendolyn Sutton Powrie papers, 1947-1972
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Emerson F. Powrie and Gwendolyn Sutton Powrie papers 1947-1972, 1956-1970
Powrie family.
(in 3 boxes)
2.5 linear feet
2010205 Aa 2
Papers of Emerson F. Powrie, Ann Arbor, MI public schools teacher (1945-1948), principal (1948-1971), and Central Administration employee (1972-1977); and his wife Gwendolyn Sutton Powrie, teacher for the hearing-impaired children.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was donated by Lyn Davidge (donor no. 6193 ) in June 2010.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Emerson F. Powrie's career with the Ann Arbor Public Schools (AAPS) began in 1945, when he was hired to teach Social Studies and coach football at Slauson Jr. High School. At the same time he became active in a statewide initiative for drivers' education and in 1947 became the first AAPS driving instructor. In 1948 he directed the drivers' education program at the Ann Arbor High School. In 1950 Powrie became Principal of Jones School. He spent the 1956/1957 academic year at the Burns Park Elementary School. In Fall 1957 he became the Wines School Principal. During his tenure at Wines, Powrie served as chair of the Jones School Reassignment Committee, charged with devising plans to implement a Board decision to close Jones School because of de facto segregation. In the early 1960s, Wines was one of about 20 schools in a six-state region participating in the experimental project, the Midwest Program on Airborne Television Instructions (MPATI), bringing televised lessons to Ann Arbor public schools for the first time. Powrie transferred to Dicken School in 1969 where he served as a Principal until the 1970/1971 academic year. In 1972 he transferred to the Central Administration and subsequently became Deputy Superintendent for Administration. Powrie was active in the Kiwanis Club of Ann Arbor; and was member of the Ann Arbor Principals Association, and Michigan Association of Elementary Schools Principals. Emerson F. Powrie died in 1977.
Gwendolyn Sutton Powrie taught at both the Michigan School for the Deaf (ca. 1934-1940) and the Rackham School at Michigan State Normal College (ca. 1950-1953). While in this last position, she also earned a Master’s degree from the University of Michigan School of Education (1953). She later taught at Tappan Jr. high School in Ann Arbor, Mich. Gwendolyn Sutton Powrie died in 1972.
The Powrie family papers have been divided into three series: Emerson F. Powrie papers; Gwendolyn Sutton Powrie papers; and Visual Materials.
The Emerson F. Powrie's papers represent the bulk of the collection. The collection follows Powrie's career as an educator and Ann Arbor Public Schools Principal, and reflects on challenges and developments that took place in Ann Arbor Public Schools system in 1950s-early 1970s. Materials shed light on process of racial desegregation in schools among students as well as faculty; important demographic, social and economic changes in the area, and their effect on the student body, (i.e., school enrollment, racial and socio-economic composition of classes, etc.). Topics of teachers' education and training, and religion in public schools are prominent in correspondence.
The Gwendolyn Sutton Powrie's papers include her writings and research materials on the subject of teaching the hearing-impaired children.
Subjects:
Powrie, Emerson F.; Powrie, Gwendolyn Sutton.; Ann Arbor Public Schools.; Dicken Elementary School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Jones School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Kiwanis Club of Ann Arbor.; Wines Elementary School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); De facto school segregation--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Educational television programs--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Elementary school teaching--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Hearing impaired children--Education--Michigan.; School integration--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Burns Park School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Dicken Elementary School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Kiwanis Club of Ann Arbor.; Slauson Junior High School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Wines Elementary School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Children--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Classrooms--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Schools--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Teachers--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
Brauckmann, Karl.; Limprecht, Marta.
Genre Terms:
Drawings.; Photograph albums.; Photographs.; Slides (photographs)
- Emerson F. Powrie papers
  The Emerson F. Powrie papers series is the largest series in the collection. It is comprised of files related to the Ann Arbor Public Schools system, the Kiwanis Club of Ann Arbor, and several Michigan organizations and governmental department.
  The administrative records of the Jones Elementary School, Wines Elementary School, and Dicken Elementary School contain enrollment numbers, studies and reports about racial and socio-economic composition of student body, and official memoranda. Also included in this series are school directories and reports, as well as Powrie's selected correspondence dating to his tenures at the Ann Arbor Public Evening School, Jones, Wines, and Dicken Elementary Schools. School files also include student and P.T.O. publications and newsletters. Other Ann Arbor Public Schools materials include records of the Ann Arbor Principals Association and the 1969/1970 Ann Arbor Public Schools budget.
  The Kiwanis Club of Ann Arbor files contain correspondence, reports, and printed materials of the Kiwanis Club.
  The Michigan organizations materials include a selection of records, correspondence, and printed materials issued by the Michigan Department of Education, Michigan Department of Conservation (currently Michigan Department of Natural Resources), Michigan Association of the Elementary School Principals, and Michigan Economic Education Workshop.
  - Ann Arbor Public Evening School
    - Correspondence 1948-1950 (Box 1)
  - Jones Elementary School
    - Correspondence 1951-1957 (Box 1)
    - Jones School Distribution Committee 1964-1965 (Box 1)
  - Wines Elementary School
    - Administrative records 1957/1958-1968/1969, undated, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Directories 1957/1958-1968/1969, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1957/1958-1968/1969, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Publications, student 1962-1963, 1968-1969, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Publications, P.T.O. 1958/1959-1968/1969, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Dicken Elementary School
    - Administrative records 1968/1969-1969/1970, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
    - Annual reports 1964/1965-1970/1971 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Directories 1968/1969-1969/1970, 1971-1972, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1969/1970-1970/1971, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Public School system
    - Budget 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - Publications and reports 1963 undated (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Principals Association 1963, 1965/1966-1968/1969, 1970-1971, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Kiwanis Club of Ann Arbor records
    - Correspondence 1953-1957, 1961-1962, 1965 (Box 1)
    - Reports 1949, 1953-1957 (Box 1)
    - Publications 1951-1958 (scattered), undated (Box 1)
  - Michigan organizations publications and correspondence
    - Michigan Department of Conservation 1957, 1959 undated (Box 1)
    - Michigan Department of Education 1958 undated (Box 1)
    - Michigan Association of Elementary School Principals 1962-1963, 1970-1972 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Economic Education Workshop 1962 (Box 1)
- Gwendolyn Sutton Powrie papers
  The Gwendolyn Sutton Powrie papers series includes her notes and writings on the subject of education of hearing-impaired children, specifically, materials dating to her tenure at the Michigan School for the Deaf in Flint, Mich. Among Gwendolyn Powrie's writings is her 1953 Master's Thesis submitted to the University of Michigan School of Education Adaptation of the Jena method of speechreading for primary deaf children.
  Research materials include typewritten English translations of Das gehörleidende Kind:wie kann es hineinwachsen in unsere Sprache und geistige Gemeinschaft by Karl Brauchmann (Jena: Gustav Fischer, 1931) and Das Silben- und Formenspiel der deutschen Sprache: seine Einspielung beim gehörleidenden Kinde nach dem Jenaer Verfahren by Karl Brauchmann and Marta Limprecht (Jena: Gustav Fischer, 1933). Also included a handbook of speech therapy Speech therapy from the bio-linguistic point of view by the University of Michigan's authors John H. Muyskens and Hattie Bell Ross (Ann Arbor: Hattie Bell Ross, c1958).
  - Michigan School for the Deaf (Flint, Mich.), notes 1933 undated (Box 2)
  - Writings
    - Adaptation of the Jena Method of speechreading for primary deaf children, 1953 (Box 2)
    - Speechreading for young deaf children: Jena Method, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Research materials
    - The child who suffers from impaired hearing: how can it become adjusted to our language and intellectual community? by Karl Brauckmann (English translation), 1931, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Syllable and grammatical-form practice in the German Language: exercises for children with impaired hearing by Karl Brauckmann and Marta Limprecht (English translation), 1933 (Box 2)
    - Speech therapy: from the bio-linguistic point of view, with organized exercises for public school classes, by John H. Muysens and Hattie Bell Ross, c1958 (Box 2)
- Visual materials
  The Visual materials series includes photographs of events, students, faculty members, school buildings and classrooms at the Slauson Middle School, Burns Park Elementary School, and Wines Elementary School; Wines Elementary School class photo albums and photo slides (with inventories). Also included drawings by Gwendolyn Powrie's students, and photographs of the Kiwanis Club of Ann Arbor.
  - Photographs and photo albums
    - Slauson Middle School 1947 (Box 2)
    - Burns Park Elementary School 1956-1957 (Box 2)
    - Wines Elementary School 1957, 1959 undated (Box 2)
    - Kiwanis Club of Ann Arbor undated (Box 2)
    - Burns Park Elementary School class photo album 1956-1957 (Box 2)
    - Wines Elementary School class photo albums 1958/1959-1968/1969, 1 folders; 12 volumes (Box 2)
    - Dicken Elementary School class photo album 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Drawings
    - Gwendolyn Sutton Powrie materials undated (Box 2)
  - Photo slides
    - Slide inventory, 1 folders (Box 3)
    - Wines Elementary School slides circa 1956-1968 scattered, 1 boxes; 7 photograph slides (Box 3)
Related Material
The papers of Gwendolyn Sutton Powrie’s mother, Ethel Baldwin Sutton, are also available at the Bentley Historical Library.